<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A shorte catechisme of Cardall Bellarmine illustrated with the images.</title>
            <title>Dichiarazione piu copiosa della dottrina cristiana. English. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, Saint, 1542-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837409</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1090:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A shorte catechisme of Cardall Bellarmine illustrated with the images.</title>
                  <title>Dichiarazione piu copiosa della dottrina cristiana. English. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, Saint, 1542-1621.</author>
                  <author>Mayr, Georg, 16th cent.</author>
                  <author>Gibbons, Richard, 1550?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 116, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed by Christophorus Mangius] VVith licence of superiours,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In Augusta :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation by Richard Gibbons of "Dottrina christiana", which is an abridgement of "Dichiarazione piu copiosa della dottrina cristiana".</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: Georg. Mayr.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon, which reads: Augustae Vindelicorum, excudebat Christophorus Mangius. Anno M.DC.XIV.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata and colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A Christian doctrine.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Catechisms --  English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1728:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1728:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORTE CATECHISME Of Card.<hi rend="sup">all</hi> Bellarmine illuſtrated with the IMAGES.</p>
            <p>In Auguſta.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith Licence of Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1614.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1728:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1728:2"/>
            <head>Lectori S.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AGNORVM &amp; Illuſtrium viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um Auguſtanorum conſilio at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſubſidio, nouae quaedam ſacrarum maginum formae, non ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guis ſumptibus comparatae ſunt, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Catechiſmus Catholicus, ſiue Doctrina Chriſtiana, non vnâ duntaxat, ſed pluribus linguis, procedente tempore, Auguſtae in lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem edi poſſet. Atque huic pio conſilio, non infeliciter rei euentus hactenus reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit. Nam intra vnius anni ſpatium, quinque linguarum editiones Catechiſticae (Germanicae nimirùm, Latinae, Graecae, Gallicae, Italicae) maximo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarium numero abſolutae ſunt, quibus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men necdum omnium deſiderio ſatisfieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit. Cùm autem eodem tempore à pluribus magni nominis viris, pro pluribus aliis linguis ac nationibus eadem opera expeteretur, non defuerunt in hac quoque vibe viri primarii, qui Catholici Catechiſmi editionem A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>glica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam cum ijsdem imaginibus ſuſcipie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dam iudicarent. Ex illa enim natione plutimi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1728:3"/> reperiuntur, qui Catholicam fidem, Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> naeque Eccleſiae authoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum fuis tot ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum laudatiſſimis Maioribus, cum tot alijs Regnis ac Prouincijs, &amp;, quod verè dici poteſt, cum maiore Orbis Chriſtiani parte, etiam nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> integrè profitentur. Nulla igitur idonea cauſa ſuppetit, cur ab huius (licet exigui) beneficii tot aliis linguis ac nationibus praeſtandi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nione ſolos Anglos excludamus. Bona autem fide exemplar Anglicanum ex Italico ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſequi conati ſumus. Quòd ſicubi erratum fuerit, facile ignoſcet is, quilibellum hunc non in Anglia, ſed in Germania à Germanis, Chriſtianae charitatis cauſa, excuſum memine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Auguſtae, 20. Septembris. Anno 1614.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Georg. Mayr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1728:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>S.</hi> GREGORIVS MAGNVS, Anglorum Apoſtolus, lib. 9. epiſtolarum, lib. 9.</head>
            <p>QVod legentibus ſcriptura hoc idio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis praeſtat pictura cernentibus: quia in ipſa etiam ignorantes vident, quod ſequi debeant: in iſta legunt, qui literas neſciunt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1728:4"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE CHRISTIAN DOCTRINE TO BELEARNED BY HEART.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the end of a Chriſtian, and of the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of the Croſſe.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARE yovv a Chriſtian?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholar.</speaker>
               <p>I am by the grace of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1728:4"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What meane yovv by</hi> a Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Him that maketh profeſſion of the Faith and Lavve of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1728:5"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In vvhat doth the Faith of Chriſt chieflie conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In tvvo principall myſteries, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the ſigne of the holy†Croſſe, that is in the <hi>Vnitie</hi> &amp; <hi>Trinitie</hi> of God: &amp; in the <hi>Incarnation</hi> &amp; <hi>death</hi> of our Sauiour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1728:5"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat meaneth</hi> Vnitie <hi>&amp;</hi> Trinitie <hi>of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It menaeth that in God there is one only Diuinitie, or, as we ſaie, Eſſence and diuine nature, which neuertheles is in three diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne perſons, that are called <hi>Father, Sonne</hi> and <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1728:6"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherfore are there three diuine perſons?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe the <hi>Father</hi> hath no benning, not proceedeth from another perſon. The <hi>Sonne</hi> proceedeth from the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Sonne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherfore are theſe three perſons one onlie God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe they haue one-ſelf eſſence, one-ſelf power, one ſelf wiſdome and one-ſelf goodnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wath meaneth</hi> incarnation <hi>and death of our Sauiour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S</speaker>
               <p>It meaneth that de <hi>Sonne</hi> of God, that is the ſecond perſon of the moſt bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie became man, and died vppon the Croſſe to ſaue vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1728:6"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hovv are theſe tvvo myſteries included in the ſigne of the holy Croſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we make the ſigne of the holy
<figure/> Croſſe putting our right hand firſt to the head ſaying. <hi>In the name of the Father,</hi> then vnder the breaſt ſaying, <hi>And of the Sonne;</hi> finallie to the lefth, &amp; right ſhoulder ſaying, <hi>And of the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1728:7"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hovv then is heere ſhevved the firſt myſtery of the moſt B. Trinitie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe this woord, <hi>In the name,</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Vnitie;</hi> the other vvords ſignifie the <hi>Trinitie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shevv nevv the ſecond?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The figure of the Croſſe doth repreſent the death of our Sauiour, who after he was made man, and had taught the vvay of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vvith doctrine, vvith example, and vvith miracles, died vppon the holy vvoode of the Croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the Creede.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHich is the Rule of beleef?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It is the Symbole of the Apoſtles, vvhich commonlie vve call the Creede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1728:7"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say the Creede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue in God the Father almightie, Creator of heauen and earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1728:8"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>And in IESVS Chriſt his onlie Sonne out Lord.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1728:8"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Whoe was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Marie.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:1728:9"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IV.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Suffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead and buried.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1728:9"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Deſcended into hel; the third day he roſe agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from death.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1728:10"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Aſcended into heauen, ſitteth at the rig hand of God the Father almightie.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1728:10"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>From thence he shall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1728:11"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1728:11"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IX.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The holy Catolique Church, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saincts.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1728:12"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>X.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1728:12"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>XI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Reſurrection of the flesh.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1728:13"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>XII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1728:13"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhoe made the Creede?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>THe tvvelue Apoſtles, &amp; therfore there be tvvelue articles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What doe theeſe articles containe in ſumme?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>All that, vvhich principallie &amp; expreſſie vve muſt beleeue of God, and of the Church his ſpouſe; becauſe the eight firſt articles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to God, the foure laſt to the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the firſt article.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I firmlie beleeue in one onlie God, vvhoe is the natural father of his onlie begotten ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and is alſo father by grace of all good Chriſtians, vvhoe are therfore called the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>optiue ſonnes of God. finally he is father by creation of all other thinges. And this God is <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> becauſe he can doe all that he vvill, and hath created of nothing Heauen and Earth, vvith vvathſoeuer is in them, that is the vvhole vniuerſal vvoorld.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſecond article.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue alſo in IESVS Chriſt, vvho is the onlie begotten Sonne of God the Father, becauſe he vvas begotten of the ſame father eternallie, and is God eternall, infinite, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, Creator, and Lord of vs, and of all things, as is the father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the third.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that IESVS Chriſt is not onlie true God bud alſo true man, becauſe he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1728:14"/> mans fleſh of the im<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aculate Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by vertue of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; ſo vvas borne in earth of mother vvithout father, as in heauen he vvas borne of father vvithout mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fourth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that IESVS Chriſt, to redeeme the vvorld vvith his pretious blood, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder Pontius Pilate Gouernour of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, being ſcourged, crovvned vvith thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and put vppon the Croſſe, on the vvich he died, and taken dovvne from the ſame vvas buried in a nevv Sepulchre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fifth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that IESVS Chriſt, as ſoone as he vvas dead, vvent vvith his ſovvle to the Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo or place of holie Fathers, &amp; the third daie, vvhich vvas the Sundaie, he roſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; triumphant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſixth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that IESVS Chriſt, after he had fortie daies remayned vvith the holie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to proue vvith manie apparitions his true Reſurrection, mounted vp to the hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſt heauen, &amp; there ſitteth aboue all the quires of Angels, at the right hand of the farher, that is, in glorie equall to the father, as Lord and Gouernour of all creatures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſeuenth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1728:14"/>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that the ſame out Lord, in the end of the vvoorld, ſhall come from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith moſt great povver and glorie, and ſhall iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geall men, giuing to euerie one the revvard or puniſhment that he hath deſerued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the eight.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt, vvho is the third perſon of the moſt bleſſed Trinitie, and proceedeth from the Father and the Sonne, and is in all and euerie thing equall to the Father, and to the Sonne; that is, he is God, Eternall, Infinite, Omnipotent, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and Lord of all things, as the Father and the Sonne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ninth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue alſo that there is a Church, vvhich is the Congregation of all faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that are baptized, doe beleeue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the faith of Chriſt ourd Lord, and ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvledge the high Biſhop of Rome for Vicar of the ſame Chriſt in earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Church vvhy is it called</hi> Holy, <hi>and</hi> Catholike?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Holy</hi> becauſe it hath the head, vvich is Chriſt, holy; and for that it hath manie holy members, and the Faith, and Lavv, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments holy; and it is called <hi>Catholike,</hi> that is Vniuerſall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:1728:15"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſignifieth the</hi> Communion of Saincts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſignifieth the participation of praiers and good vvoorks, that are done in that Church; euen as in a mans body all the members be partakers of the good of one member.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the tenth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that in the holy Cuurch there is the true remiſſion of ſinnes, by meanes of the holy Sacraments, and that in the ſame, men, of children of the diuel, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, become the children of God, and heyres of Paradiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the eleuenth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that in the end of the vvoorld all men ſhall riſe, taking againe the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, vvich before they had, and this by the povver of God, to vvhom nothing is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that for good Chriſtians there is life euerlaſting full of all felicitie, and free from all ſort of euill; as contrarie vviſe for infidels, and for euill Chriſtians, there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, repleniſhed vvith all miſerie, and void of all good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What meane you by</hi> Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I meane. So is it in truth.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1728:15"/>
               <head>A DECLARATION OF THE <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> and of the <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAuing ſpoken novv of that vvhich vve muſt beleeue, let vs ſee yf yovv knovv that vvhich vve muſt hope for, and of whome vve muſt haue hope. Knovv you the</hi> Pater noſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I knovv it right vvel, for this is the firſt thing that I learned, and I ſay it euerie mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, together vvith the <hi>Aue Maria</hi> and vvith the <hi>Creede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:1728:16"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say then the Pater noſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>OVr Father vvhich art in heauen. Halovved be thy name.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:1728:16"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thy kingdome come.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:1728:17"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thy vvill be donne in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:1728:17"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Giue vs this daie our dailie bread.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1728:18"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>And forgiue vs our debts, as vve alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our debters.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1728:18"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>And leade vs not into tentation.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1728:19"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>But deliuer vs from euil, Amen.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1728:19"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhoe made this praier?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>CHriſt our Sauiour made it, and therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it is the moſt excellent of all others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat is brieflie conteined in this praier?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>All that we can demaund, and hope for of God. For there be ſeuen petitions. In the firſt foure we demaund that he giue vs all good: in the three folovving that he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from all euill. And concerning that which is good, we firſt demaund the glorie of God. Secondlie our greateſt good. Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlie grace to obtaine it. Fourthlie the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to get and keepe the ſaid grace. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is euill, we demaund that he deliuer vs firſt from euil paſt; ſecondlie from euil to come; thirdlie from euil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſo from all euil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare thoſe vvoords that goe before the firſt petition, that is,</hi> Our father which art in heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a little preface, in which is yealded the reaſon, wherfore we haue couradge to ſpeake vnto ſo great a Lord, and hope he will graunt our requeſt. We ſ y then that God is our Father by Creation, and Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therfore as children we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to him; and we add that he is in heauen as Lord of the vniuerſall world.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1728:20"/> And for this vve knovv that he can graunt our petition, if it ſo pleaſe him, as vve doe hope he vvill, ſeing that he is our father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the firſt petition.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>In the firſt petition, vve demaund that God be knovve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the vvorld, and that ſo his holy name be honoured, &amp; glorified of all, at is becometh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſecond.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the ſecond that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vvhich he hath promiſed vs, come ſpeedilie, vvhich is to ſay, that the battailes ended, vvhich vve haue vvith the diuel, vvith the vvorld, and vvith the flesh, vve may arriue to euerlaſting felicitie, vvhere vve shall raigne vvith God vvithout anny impediment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the third.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the third the grace of God, vvith vvhich vve may perfectlie obey his holy commaundements, as the Angels doe alvvaies obey him in heauen. Becauſe the ladder, to mount vp to heauen, is the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his commaundements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fourth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the fourth our dailie bread as vvel ſpirituall, that is the vvoord of God and the Sacraments; as corporall, that is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinance and apparel. For the vvoord of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1728:20"/> God preached vnto vs by preachers, and read by vs in ſpirituall bookes, &amp; the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, chieflie of Confeſſion and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, at moſt efficatious meanes of their part (that is, yf vve our ſelues be not in fault) to obtaine and conſerue the grace of God, of vvhich vve haue ſpoken in the former petition. Suſtinance &amp; apparel is neceſſarie for vs, to maintaine this life in the ſeruice of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fifth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the fifth that God deliuer vs from euils paſt, that is from ſinnes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die committed, remitting vs the debt of the fault, and of the paine, vvhich for them vve haue incurred. And vve add, As vve forgiue our debters their debts, that is, as vve pardon the offenſes of our enemies: for that it is not a reaſonable thing, that God forgiue vs our ſinnes, vvhich ar moſt great offenſes, yf vve vvil not pardon the injuries donne vnto vs, vvhich ar offenſes of ſmall importan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſixth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the ſixth, that God deliuer vs from tentations vvhich ar euils to come, or not permitting vs to be tented, or giuing vs grace that vve be not ouercome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1728:21"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſeuenth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We demaund in the ſeuenth that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euil preſent, that is from al affliction and miſerie and alſo from all vail ne proſperitie and temporall aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yf he ſee that it be hurtfull to our ſovvles ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:1728:21"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say novv the Aue Maria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Haile MARIE full of grace; Our Lord is vvith thee; bleſſed art thou amongſt vvomen, And bleſſed is the fruite of thy vvombe IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:1728:22"/>
                  <p>Holy MARIE mother of God pray for vs
<figure/> ſinners, novv, and in the hovver of our death. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1728:22"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of vvhome be theeſe vvoords?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be partlie of the Archangel Gabriel partlie of S. Elizabeth, and partlie of th Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tho vvhat effect doe yovv ſay the</hi> Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>afther the</hi> Pater noſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Tho the end that by the interceſſion of the moſt bleſſed Virgin, I may more eaſilie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that vvhich I demaund of God, beacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſhee is the Aduocatrice of ſinners, full of mercie, and vvithall is in heauen aboue all the quires of Angels, and moſt acceptable to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haue not yovv recourſe for help alſo to other Saincts?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue recourſe to all the Saincts, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to the Sainct of my name, and to my Angel guardian.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>OF THE COMMAVNDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEt vs come novv to that, vvhich vve muſt doe to loue God and our neighbour, and ſay yovv the ten Commaundements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I am the Lord thy God.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1728:23"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not haue any other God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:1728:23"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not take the name of God in vaine.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1728:24"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Remember that thou ſanctifie the feſtes.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1728:24"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Honour thy father and mother.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:1728:25"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not murder.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:1728:25"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not committ adulterie.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1728:26"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not ſteale.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1728:26"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not beare falſe vvitneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:1728:27"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IX.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not deſire thy neigbours vvife.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1728:27"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>X.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Thou shalt not couet thy neighbours goods.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:1728:28"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhoe hath giuen theeſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>GOd him-ſelf in the old lavve, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards Chriſt our Lord hath confirmed them in the nevv lavve.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat doe theeſe commaundements conteine in breefe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>All that vvhich vve muſt doe to loue God &amp; our neighbour. Becauſe the firſt three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements teache vs hovv vve ought to behaue our ſelues tovvards God, vvith hart, vvith mouth, &amp; vvith vvoorcks. The other feue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe learne vs to doe good to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and not to hurt him in his perſon, in his honour, in his goods, neither in deedes, nor in vvoords, nor in thought. And ſo the end of all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of Charitie, vvhich doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund vs loue God aboue all things, and our neighbour as our ſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the firſt commandement.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>In the beginning God doth admoniſh vs, that he is our true and ſupreame Lord, and therfore vve are obliged to obey him vvith all diligence. Next he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs, that vve muſt not acknovvlegde any other for God; vvherin the Infidels doe ſinne, vvho vvoorſhip the creatures in ſteede of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; and alſo vvitches and Inchanters, vvho take the diuel for their God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:1728:28"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſecond commaundement.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement forbiddeth bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies, vvhich are moſt grieuous ſinnes; falſe, or not neceſſarie oathes; breaking of vovves; and all other diſhonour that is don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to God vvith vvoords.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the third.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The third doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund the keeping of feaſtes, vvhich doth conſiſt in abſtaining from ſeruile vvoorcks, ſo to haue time to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie our ſelues in conſidering the benefits of God, viſiting the Churchs, praying, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſpirituall bookes, hearing diuine ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; ſermons, &amp; dooing ſuch other like ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and holy vvoorcks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fourth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The fourth ordaineth, that vve honour our father &amp; mother, not onlie vvith reuerence of vvoords, of vncouering our head to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but alſo vvith helping and fauouring them in their neceſſities. And that vvhich vve ſay of father and mother, vve ought alſo to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue tovvards other our neighbours, altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh there be not ſo great obligation as to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, vvho haue giuen vs our being, and haue brought vs vp vvith their great paine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the fifth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>In the fifth it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that vve kill no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1728:29"/> boddie vniuſtlie, nor doe them other harme in their perſon: &amp; I ſay vniuſtlie, becauſe Iudges vvho condemne malefactours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath, and the miniſtres of Iuſtice, vvho put them to death, as alſo ſouldiars in iuſt vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, doe not ſinne vvhileſt they vvound and kill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſixth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſixth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth that vve co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit not adulterie, that is ſinne vvith the vvife of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: and it is alſo vnderſtoode that vve commit not fornication, nor anie other car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the ſeuenth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſeuenth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth, that no man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke avvay the goods of others ſecreatlie, vvhich is called Theft; nor manifeſtlie, vvhich is called Robberie; not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit annie deceite in ſelling, bying, and like contracts; and finallie doe no harme to his neighbour in his goods.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the eigth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>In the eigth is forbidden falſe vvitneſſe, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, detracting, flattering, lying, and all other hurt vvhich is donne to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vvith the tongue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare the tvvo laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth in the thvvo laſt precepts, that none deſire the vvife, nor goods of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1728:29"/> becauſe he that ſeeeth our hearts, vvill haue vs holy &amp; cleane, not onlie outvvardlie, but alſo invvardlie, that ſo vve may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierlie and trulie iuſt.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Commaundements of the Church, and of Counſels.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADd to the Commaundements of God, thoſe fevve vvhich the Church hath added</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>The Commaundments of the holy Church are ſix,</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:1728:30"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>1.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Tho heare maſſe vppon all the Sundaies, &amp; Holie daies of commaundement.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:1728:30"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>2.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To faſt Lent, Vigills commaunded, &amp; Ember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, &amp; not to eat fleſh on fridaies &amp; Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turdaies.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:1728:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>3. &amp; 4.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To confeſſe, at the leſt, once a yeare.</p>
               <p>To receaue, at the leſt, at Eaſter.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:1728:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>5.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To paye tithes.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:1728:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:1728:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:1728:33"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>6.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Not to celebrate marriage in time forbidden that is from the firſt Sundaie of Adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vntill Tvvelfday, &amp; from the firſt day of Lent to Lovv-ſundaie incluſiue.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:1728:33"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beſides the Commaundments, vvhich vve all are bound to keepe, be there annie Counſels of Perfection?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>There be three Counſels, by our Sauiour Chriſt giuen to thoaſe that deſire to attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to perfection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:1728:34"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhich be theeſe Counſels?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Voluntarie Pouertie.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:1728:34"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Perpetuall Chaſtitie.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:1728:35"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Obedience in euerie thing that is not ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:1728:35"/>
               <head>OF THE SACRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We haue alreddie treated of all that which vve muſt beleeue, hope for, &amp; dooe; it remaineth that vve ſpeake of the holie Sacraments, by vvhoſe meanes vve obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the grace of God. Say therfore, hovv manie be the Sacraments?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be ſeuen.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:1728:36"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Baptiſme.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:1728:36"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Confirmation.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:1728:37"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Euchariſt.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:1728:37"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Penance.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:1728:38"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Extreme Vnction.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:1728:38"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Ordre.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:1728:39"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Matrimonie.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:1728:39"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhoe ordained them?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Chriſt IESVS our Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect doth Baptiſme vvorck?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It maketh a man become the child of God and heire of Paradiſe: it blotteth out all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and filleth the ſoule with grace and ſpirituall gifts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect doth Confirmation or Chriſme vvoorck?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It fortifieth a man that he be not afraid to confeſſe the faith of Chriſt our Lord, and ſo it maketh vs become the true ſouldiars of our Sauiour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect vvoorcketh the Euchariſt?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It nourriſheth Charitie, vvhich is the life of the ſovvle, &amp; doth dailie increaſe it more. And therfore it is giuen vnder the forme of bread; though trulie it be not bread, but the true bodie of our Lord: as likevviſe that vvhich is in the chalice, is not vvine, albeit it ſeeme vvine, but it is the true bloud of the ſame Chriſt our Lord vnder the forme of vvine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect vvorcketh Penance?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It forgiueth ſinnes committed after Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; bringeth againe to the frendſhip of God him, who thorough ſinne vvas beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me his enemie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:1728:40"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat muſt vve doe to receaue this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>We muſt firſt haue ſorovve for ovvne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, with purpoſe neuer more to commit them. Then vve muſt confeſſe them all to a Prieſt approued by Superiors; and finallie vve muſt doe the penance that is inioyned vs by the Prieſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect doth Extreme Vnction vvoorck?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It blotteth out the reliques of ſinnes; giueth ioye and ſtrength to the ſovvle, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the diuell in the laſt hovver; and alſo helpeth to recouer bodilie health, if it be ſo expedient for the ſaluation of the ſovvle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What effect vvoorcketh the Sacrament of Order?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It giueth vertue and grace to Prieſts and other miniſters of the Church, to be able to doe vvell their duties.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat effect vvorcketh the Sacrament of Matrimonie?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It giueth vertue and grace to thoſe that be lavvfullie ioined together, to liue in matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie vvith peace and charitie, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett, and bring vp their children in the holy feare of God, to the end they may haue ioy in this life and in the other.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:1728:40"/>
               <head>Of Theologicall and Cardinall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE haue novv ended the foure principall parts of the Chriſtian Doctrine vvhich be the</hi> Creede, <hi>the</hi> Pater noſter, <hi>the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>and the</hi> Sacraments. <hi>I vvill novv that vve talk of</hi> Vertues <hi>and</hi> Vices, <hi>of ſome other things vvhich doe help vs much to liue conformablie to the vvill of God. Tell me therfore, Hovv manie be the principall Vertues?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be ſeuen; Three Theologicall, and foure Cardinall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhich be the Theologicall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, Hope, and Charitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVerfore be they called Theologicall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe this vvoord Theologicall ſignifieth a thing, that regardeth or appertaineth to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv doth faith then appertaine to God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe it maketh vs beleeue all that, vvhich God hath reueiled to the holy Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVherfore doth Hope pertaine to God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe it maketh vs put our truſt in God, and hope eternall life of him, by meanes of our merites, vvhich yet doe proceede from his grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhy doth Charitie pertaine to God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe it maketh vs loue God aboue all-things
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1728:41"/> things, and our neighbour as our ſelues, for the loue of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which be the Cardinall vertues?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Prudence, Iuſtice, Fortitude and Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why be they called Cardinall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe they be principall, and as it vvere the fountaines of Good vvoorcks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare vnto me the office of theeſe vertues?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Prudence maketh vs conſiderate &amp; vvarie in euerie thing, to the end vve our ſelues be not deceiued, nor deceiue others. Iuſtice maketh vs render vnto others, that vvhich is theires. Temperance maketh vs bridle our diſordinate deſires. Fortitude maketh that vve feare not annie daunger, no nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath it ſelfe for Gods ſeruice.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the gifts of holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HOvv manie be the gifts of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be ſeuen.
<list>
                        <item>1. Wiſdome.</item>
                        <item>2. Vnderſtanding.</item>
                        <item>3. Counſaile.</item>
                        <item>4. Fortitude.</item>
                        <item>5. Knovvlegde.</item>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:1728:41"/>
                        <item>6. Pietie.</item>
                        <item>7. Feare of God.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhereto doe theeſe gifts ſerue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They ſerue for the help of vertues, &amp; to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs perfect in the vvay of God, becauſe through feare vve abſteine from ſinnes: through Pietie vve are devoure &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to God; through Knovvledge vve are taught to vnderſtand the vvill of God; through For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude vve are holpen to put the ſame in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; through <hi>Counſaile</hi> vve are admoniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed of the deceits of the diuell; through <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> vve are eleuated to penetrate the myſteries of faith; through <hi>VViſdome</hi> vve become perfect ordaining all our life, &amp; all our vvoorks to the glorie of God, becauſe the vviſeman doth knovv the laſt end, &amp; the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunto doth direct euerie thing.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the vvoorks of mercie.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>HOvv many be the vvoorks of mercy of vvhich vve ſhalbe demaunded account in particular at the day of iudgment?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They be ſeuen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:1728:42"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To giue to eate to the hungrie.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:1728:42"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To giue to trincke to the Thirſtie.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:1728:43"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To cloth the naked.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:1728:43"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To harbour pilgrimes.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:1728:44"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To viſit the ſicke.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:1728:44"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To viſit the impriſoned.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:1728:45"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To burie the dead.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:1728:45"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theeſe be corporall woorks of mercie: be there anie others ſpirituall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>There be other ſeuen that is. I.</p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>1. To giue counſaile to the dout full.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:1728:46"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>2.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To inſtruct the ignorant.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:1728:46"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>3.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To admonish ſinners.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:1728:47"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>4.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To comfort the afflicted.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:1728:47"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>5.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To pardon offences.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:1728:48"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>6.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To patientlie ſupport thoſe that be troubleſome.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:1728:48"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>7.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To pray God for the quicke and dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:1728:49"/>
               <head>Of Sinnes.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TO come novv to Sinnes, hovv manie ſorts be there of them?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Two, <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Actual,</hi> which is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards diuided into <hi>Mortal</hi> and <hi>Venial.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is</hi> Originall <hi>ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that with which we at all borne, and we haue it as it were by heritage from our firſt Father Adam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv is this ſinne blotted out?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>VVith holie Baptiſme. And therfore he that dieth without Baptiſme goeth to Limbus, and is depriued for euer from the glorie of Heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat is Mortall ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that Which we commit againſt the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of God, or of our neighbour. And it is called mortall, becauſe it depriueth the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wle of her ſpirituall life, which is the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv is this ſinne forgiuen vs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>VVith holie Baptiſme, when a man is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in age to haue committed ſinne actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; or vvith the Sacramento of Penance as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1728:49"/> hath ben ſaid before. And vvho dieth in mortall ſinne, goeth to the euerlaſting paines of hell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhich is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eniall ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that vvhich is not againſt Charitie, and depriueth not the ſovvle of grace, nor ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it to the paines of hell: but neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it diſpleaſeth God, becauſe it is not con<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his vvill, and it diminiſheth the feruour of charitie, And therfore it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to purge it in this vvoorld, or in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, vvhich is in the other life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv many be the Capitall ſinnes &amp; as it vvere fountaines of all ſinnes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be ſeuen, and to euerie one is oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a contrarie vertue.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:1728:50"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Pride, to which is contrarie Humilitie.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:1728:50"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Couetouſnes, to vvhich is contrarie Liberalitie.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:1728:51"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Lecherie, to vvhich is oppoſite Chaſtitie.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:1728:51"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Angre, to vvhich it oppoſite Patience.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:1728:52"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>V.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Gloutonie, to vvhich is oppoſite Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:1728:52"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VI.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Enuie, to vvhich is oppoſite brotherlie loue.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:1728:53"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>VII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Slouth, to vvhich is oppoſite Diligence.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:1728:53"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How manie be the ſinnes againſt the holie Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be ſix.</p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>1.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Deſpaire of Saluation.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:1728:54"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>2.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Preſumption to be ſaued vvithout merites.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:1728:54"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>3.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To impugne the knovven truth.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:1728:55"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>4.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Enuie at an other mans grace.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:1728:55"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>5.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Obſtination in ſinne.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:1728:56"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>6.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Finall impenitence.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:1728:56"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv manie be the ſinnes that crie vengeance in the ſight of God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>They be foure.</p>
               </sp>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>VVillfull murder.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:1728:57"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Carnall ſinne againſt nature.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:1728:57"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Oppreſſion of the poore.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:1728:58"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IIII.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>To defraude woorkmen of their vvages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:1728:58"/>
               <head>Of the foure last things, and of the Roſarie.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HOw mannie be the laſt things of man which the Scripture calleth laſt, which being well conſidered doe make vt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>Foure.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:1728:59"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>I.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Death.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:1728:59"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>II.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Iudgment.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:1728:60"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:1728:60"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:1728:61"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>III.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Hell.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:1728:61"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>IV.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Heauen.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:1728:62"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat exerciſe haue you to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine deuotion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaie the Roſarie of our Ladie, and doe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate the fifteene myſteries of the ſame, in vvhich is contained the life of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhich be the fifteene Myſteries of the Roſarie?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>There be fiue loifull. 1. The Annuntiation of the Angel. 2. The Viſitation of S. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. 3. The Natiuitie of our Lord. 4. The Preſentation in the Temple. 5. The diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the child IESVS with the Doctors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Other fiue be ſorowfull</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The praier in the garden. 2. The whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at the pillar. 3. The crowning with thornes 4. The carying of the Croſſe. 5. The crucifying and death of our Sauiour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The laſt fiue be glorious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Reſurrection of our Lord. 2. His Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion. 3. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the holy Ghoſt. 4. The Aſſumption of our Ladie. 5. The coronation and exaltation of her aboue all the quites of Angels.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:1728:62"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 23. expreslie. but. 25. Father. 38. vaine. 41. becauſe. 52. com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aund. 53 Two. 56. To. 73 giuen. 75. Wherfore. 76. of the holy, 97. is. 107. in te ſight.</p>
            <p>Caetera lector Anglus typographo Germano ignoſcet.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>BENEFICENTIAE. ET COMMVN: NOLITE. OBLIVISCI.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Auguſtae Vindelicorum, <hi>Excudebat Chriſtophorus Mangius.</hi> ANNO M.DC.XIV.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
